Guide to the Amber Arthun Warburton Papers, 1917-1976 and undated RL.01341
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Amber Arthun Warburton papers
1917-1976 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Warburton, Amber Arthun, 1898-1976
RL.01341
35 Linear Feet
circa 31,400 Items
Teacher, librarian, specialist in economics, labor, and education; New Deal administrator. Correspondence, diaries, writings, interviews, drafts of studies and reports, scrapbooks, printed material, photographs, and other papers, relating to Warburton's leadership in the Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth (AGRY), 1947-1963; and to Affiliated Schools for Workers, Atlanta University, Brookwood Labor College, Columbia University (M.A., 1927), Institute of Social and Religious Research, Mount Holyoke College, Summer School for Women Workers in Industry, Spelman College, U.S. Children's Bureau, U.S. Federal Emergency Relief Administration, and the U.S. House Committee on Agriculture. Topics include the rural youth guidance movement, training programs for unemployed teachers in the 1930s, women workers in the 1920s, African Americans in the early 1930s, industrial home work in the Northeast in the late 1930s, migrant farm workers in the Southwest and Florida in the 1940s to 1950s, socioeconomic conditions in coal mining villages in Pennsylvania, Ohio, and Illinois in the late 1920s, and in Harlan County, Ky., and Green Sea, S.C., in the late 1940s, and the effects of the National Defense Education Act on guidance in rural high schools.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Warburton Papers were presented to Duke University by Clark Warburton, husband of Amber Warburton, in 1977.
Biographical Note
Chronology
May, 1898 Born in Seattle, Washington
June, 1920 Graduated from the University of Washington with a bachelor of business administration degree.
1921-1922 Taught social science at a high school in Kimberly, Idaho.
1922-1923 Taught social science at a high school in Fairfield, Washington.
Sept., 1923 - Oct., 1925 Librarian at Brookwood Labor College, Katonah, New York.
Oct., 1925 - June, 1926 Traveled and studied in Europe.
June, 1926 - Feb., 1929 Studied at Columbia University. Received M.A. in Economics in 1927 and completed resident requirements for the Ph.D. in 1929.
Feb., 1928 - June, 1928 Taught economics and sociology at Mount Holyoke College.
Summer of 1927, 1928, and 1929 Taught labor problems at Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry.
March, 1929 - Aug., 1929 Investigated social and economic conditions in coal mining villages of Ohio, Illinois, and Pennsylvania for study sponsored by the Institute of Social and Religious Research.
Summer 1929 Married Clark Warburton, an economist.
Sept., 1929 - June, 1932 Taught economics at Spelman College and Atlanta University.
March, 1930 Investigated social and economic conditions in a rural-industrial Georgia county for the Institute of Social and Religious Research.
July, 1932 - July, 1933 Assisted in preparation of Dr. Louis Lorwin's American Federation of Labor: History, Policies, and Prospects.
June, 1934 - July, 1934 Directed Federal Teacher Training Center in Workers' Education in Atlanta, Georgia.
Aug., 1934 - Sept., 1934 Directed Federal Teacher Training Center in Workers' Education in Gulfport, Mississippi.
Apr., 1935 - May, 1935 Evaluated workers' education program and helped train teachers in Detroit, Michigan.
June, 1935 - July, 1935 Taught economics at Bryn Mawr Summer School for Women in Industry in Mount Ivy, New York.
Aug., 1935 - Sept., 1935 Directed Federal Teacher Training Center in Workers' Education in Logan, Utah.
Oct., 1935 - Aug., 1939 Active in Washington civic organizations.
Sept., 1939 - Aug., 1943 Associate researcher in Special Studies Unit of the Children's Bureau, United States Department of Labor, Washington, D.C. Supervised field work and wrote reports for two published studies: Industrial Home-Work Conditions in the Candlewick Bedspread and Lace Industries (1940) and Work and Welfare of Children of Agricultural Laborers in Hidalgo County, Texas (1943).
Sept., 1943 - Jan., 1946 Active in Fairfax County, Virginia, school and civic affairs.
Feb., 1946 - Sept., 1946 Wrote report on Education for Migrant Children in the Cotton Belt for the U.S. House of Representatives Committee on Agriculture.
Feb., 1947 - Sept., 1963 Executive secretary and director of research for the Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth (AGRY). She held the positions until the organization disbanded in Sept., 1963. During her tenure, she wrote three books on AGRY-sponsored projects: Guidance in a Rural Community (1952), Guidance in a Rural-Industrial Community (1954), and Stimulating Guidance in Rural Schools (1964).
1963-1976 Retired in McLean, Virginia.
January, 1976 Died in Washington, D.C.
Collection Overview
The Amber (Arthun) Warburton Papers consist of the personal and professional papers of Warburton from 1917 to 1976. The bulk of the material comes from the organizational files of the Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth during Warburton's tenure as executive secretary and director of research, 1947-1963. Other organizations and institutions represented include Atlanta University, Brookwood Labor College, Columbia University (where she received her M.A. in 1927), Mount Holyoke College, Spelman College, Institute of Social and Religious Research, Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry, Affiliated Schools for Workers, the Federal Emergency Relief Administration, and the U.S. Children's Bureau.
The Warburton Papers contain correspondence, financial statements, writings, interviews, notes, drafts of studies and reports, newspaper clippings, newsletters, printed material, books, magazines, photographs, diaries, and scrapbooks. Most of the papers are printed material. Also includes her diploma from Columbia (1927), and an oversize photograph of the Three Fates Greek scuplture.
The papers are divided into the following thirteen series:
Series
Personal
Brookwood Labor College
Columbia University
Mount Holyoke College
Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry
Institute of Social and Religious Research
Spelman College and Atlanta University
Federal Emergency Relief Administration
Affiliated Schools for Workers
U.S. Children's Bureau
Fairfax County
U.S. House of Representatives Committee on Agriculture
Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth
Warburton's connection with these organizations and institutions is noted in the description of each series.
The largest series is the Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth Series (AGRY). The series is arranged by subject, in keeping with the arrangement pattern of a 1949 office files index. There are three major subjects within the series: Harlan County (Kentucky), Green Sea (South Carolina), and the National Defense Education Act Study. Each subject contains correspondence, notes, drafts of reports and studies, reports and studies, newspaper clippings, and printed material.
There is overlap among series, especially within the AGRY series. For instance, Warburton might correspond with one person in Green Sea about the Green Sea Institute and later about an upcoming guidance convention. Each letter would probably be found in different subjects: the Green Sea letter under Green Sea Institute, and the convention letter under material about guidance conventions.
The Warburton Papers are a rich source of information on the growth and development of the youth guidance movement in America, especially guidance in rural areas. If combined with the Duke Library's collection of early AGRY papers, a researcher could follow the American rural youth guidance movement from inception to maturation. Furthermore, the numerous surveys conducted in Harlan County and Green Sea contain much material on the socio-economic status and attitudes of people in those communities in the 1940's and 1950's, which may be valuable to the sociologist or historian studying Appalachia or the rural South.
Other highlights include considerable information on the creation, growth, and management of workers' schools and federal training centers for unemployed teachers in the 1930's; in-depth studies of industrial home-work in the Northeast and migrant workers in Texas, Arkansas, and Florida; and excellent pictures of schools, houses, and people in Harlan County and Green Sea. There are also photographs in the Personal, Columbia University, Spelman College and Atlanta University, U.S. Children's Bureau, and Fairfax County series.
Specific subjects are discussed in more detail in the inventory.
Note on Processing and Arrangement
This collection is arranged topically. Because all non-AGRY material was unorganized, series of related material had to be created. Consequently, there is some overlapping within the collection, especially among printed material from the 1930's and 1940's. For instance, printed material from New Deal programs is found in both the Federal Emergency Relief Administration and Affiliated Schools for Workers series. Still, each series corresponds to a job or period in Warburton's life, so there is a definite pattern and coherency to the arrangement of the collection.
There are several aids to the content and arrangement of the collection. First, when a folder has a heading like Printed Material, 1928-1935 (p. 13), the heading means that there is general or miscellaneous printed material in the folder from 1928 to 1935. Secondly, some subjects in a series are lengthy enough to require a centered heading, sometimes followed by an explanatory note. At the end of the material under this heading, two lines are skipped before returning to the continuation of the series. Thirdly, the years for which there is material pertaining to a series is noted under the series title. The years, however, do not necessarily correspond to Warburton's association with the organization or institution. Finally, the term Family Schedules refers to printed forms that list such things as the number of people in a family, their ages and occupations, their schooling, and so on. These schedules are found in several series.
Related Material
The Records of the Alliance for the Guidance of Rural Youth, 1887-1963 21.2 Linear Feet; circa 15,900 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Durham, NC 27708
Appalachian region -- Economic conditions -- 20th century; Education -- United States; Education, Rural -- Appalachian region; Education, Rural -- United States; Migrant agricultural laborers -- United States -- Economic conditions; Miners -- United States -- Economic conditions; New Deal, 1933-1939; United States -- Economic conditions; United States -- Race relations; United States -- Rural conditions; United States -- Social conditions; Women -- Employment -- Regional disparities; Women government executives -- United States; Women -- United States -- Diaries; Diaries; Black-and-white photographs; Institute of Social and Religious Research; Brookwood Labor College (Katonah, N.Y.); Southern Woman's Educational Alliance (U.S.); Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth (U.S.); Affiliated Schools for Workers
- Personal Series, 1920-1976
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence, writings, printed material, clippings, photographs, and volumes. The correspondence spans most of Warburton's life, but offers few special glimpses into her personal life. Interesting material in this series includes Warburton's employment applications (they provide good descriptions of her many positions), an assortment of articles on labor and unions in the 1920's and 1930's, and a series of articles by Agnes Meyer on conditions in the postwar (1946) South. There are four Warburton diaries, none of which is particularly long or revealing. There are also many photographs of Warburton and her friends and relatives.
  - Correspondence, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1965 and undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Writings. Poems, 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Information (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subject Files
    The subject files are arranged first chronologically, then alphabetically by topic. They cover a wide range of materials reflecting Amber Warburton's personal and professional interests. The bulk consists of printed materials and clippings with some letters and other miscellaneous items; there is also one folder of photographs of the Warburton family, a large photograph of a classical sculpture, and a set of diaries. Some of these materials relate to time Amber Warburton spent in Europe.
    - Subject Files, 1928-1930
      - A.F.L. - Injunctions (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Labor Legislation - Workmen's Compensation (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Subject Files, 1930-1950
      - Columbia University, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Columbia University, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Drama, 1930's (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Economic Security. Outlines and Notes, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Economic Security. Outlines and Notes, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Employment Applications of Amber Warburton, 1935-1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Hilda Smith's Poems - Social Lists (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - United Negro College Fund Campaign, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Warburton, Peter. School Material, 1935-1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Washington Consumers Conference, 1938,and Washington League of Women Shoppers, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Subject Files, 1950-1970
      - McLean Citizens Association, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Safeway Controversy, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Miscellany. Diaries, Schedules, and Assorted Printed Material from Europe, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Miscellany. Large printed photograph of Three Fates classical sculpture, early 20th century (Oversize-folder 2)
    - Miscellany, 1926-1973 and undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Clippings. Agnes Meyer Articles, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Clippings. Washington League of Women Shoppers, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Clippings, 1935-1940 and undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Printed Material. Booklets by Hilda Smith, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Printed Material. Songs (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Printed Material. Articles, Reprints, and Pamphlets, 1930's (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material. Articles, Reprints, and Pamphlets, 1940's (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Printed Material. Articles, Reprints, and Pamphlets, 1950-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Photographs. The Warburtons and unidentified people, places, and buildings, 1920s-1960s? (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Volumes. Amber Warburton's diaries, 1921 and 1936 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Volumes, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Volumes, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Volumes, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Brookwood Labor college Series, 1923-1933
  This series consists of printed material from the Brookwood Labor College. The Brookwood Labor College was an educational institution for workers founded in 1921 in Katonah, New York. Warburton was the school librarian for two years, 1923-1925.
  Within the series are pamphlets about Brookwood; articles, plays, and poems by Brookwood faculty members and students; and nine issues of the school newspaper, The Brookwood Review. There are several memorandums addressing the problem of the split between the faculty of the college and some prominent trade unionists. In general, a split developed because William Green, president of the A.F.L., accused the faculty of espousing communism. The faculty denied the charge.
  - Miscellany. Issues Papers, Plays, and Poems, 1926-1932 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellany, 1923-1933 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Columbia University Series, 1917-1932
  Warburton was a graduate student at Columbia University from 1926 to 1929. This series contains printed material from courses, Warburton's master of arts thesis (1927) and drafts of her doctoral dissertation, and reports, notes, and printed material for her dissertation. Also includes her 1927 diploma.
  - Course Materials, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Course Materials, 1926-1927 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Course Materials, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Course Materials, 1928-1929 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Writings. Warburton's Master of Arts Thesis, The Development of Trade Union Organization Among the Millinery Workers in New York City (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Writings. Draft of a study of the New York Women's Trade Union League (NYWTUL) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reports and Notes for Study of the NYWTUL (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Reports Received for Study of the NYWTUL (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material for Study of the NYWTUL (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Printed Material for Study of the NYWTUL (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Printed Material for Study of the NYWTUL (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of Mabel Leslie (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Columbia M.A. diploma, 1927 (Oversize-folder 2)
- Mount Holyoke College Series, 1928
  This series consists of notes, outlines, and bibliographies for courses taught by Warburton at Mount Holyoke College in 1928.
  - Miscellaneous Material from a Course on Economics and Sociology, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellany, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry Series, 1927-1935
  This series contains course reports, notes, and outlines, scrapbooks, pamphlets, booklets, and three issues of The News from the Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry. Warburton taught at six-week summer sessions held in Sweet Briar, Virginia in 1927, and Burnsville, North Carolina, in 1928 and 1929. Warburton also taught in a similar program in the summer of 1935, the Bryn Mawr Summer School for Women in Industry held in Mount Ivy, New York. Printed material from that program is included in this series. Additional material about this organization is in the Alice Mary Baldwin Papers in the Duke University Archives. Researchers interested in social history would find the student scrapbooks, where students often wrote short essays on their youth and work experiences, a rich source of information on Southern women workers in the late 1920's and early 1930's.
  - Printed Material. Scrapbooks, 1927-1929 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material. Scrapbooks, 1931-1933 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material. Reports, Outlines, and Syllabuses, 1929-1935 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Printed Material, 1928-1935 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Institute of Social and Religious Research Series, 1929-1930
  This series contains correspondence, notes, reports, schedules, and printed material pertaining to Warburton's field study of coal mining villages in Pennsylvania, Ohio, and Illinois in 1929 and a rural-industrial county in Georgia in 1930. Warburton was one of several investigators sent out to small industrial villages to study the churches and their roles in the villages. Though researchers were supposed to concentrate on churches, Warburton devoted much attention to social and economic conditions in the villages. Consequently, there is some revealing descriptive and statistical information on the villages Warburton visited. There is also printed material from the United Mine Workers.
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Miscellany, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Writings. Study of Warrior Run, Pennsylvania, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Notes and Schedules. Pennsylvania, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Printed Material. Pennsylvania, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Notes and Schedules. Ohio, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Notes, Schedules, and Clippings. Illinois, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Printed Material. Illinois, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Miscellany. Georgia, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - United States Children's Bureau Series, 1929-1944
    This series has correspondence, notes, family schedules, drafts of reports and studies, printed material, and photographs from Warburton's work for the Children's Bureau, 1939-1942. The bulk of the material is printed reports, either done or received by the Children's Bureau. While at the Bureau, Warburton supervised two studies that eventually were published: Industrial Homework Conditions in the Candlewick-Bedspread and Lace Industries, and Work and Welfare of Children of Agricultural Laborers in Hidalgo County, Texas. Material from the Hidalgo County study provides a penetrating view of social and economic conditions in south Texas in the early 1940's. Besides the copious printed material from the study, there are many photographs, some of which are quite good.
    - Correspondence and Notes, 1940-1944 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Reports and Studies, 1940 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Reports and Studies, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Reports and Studies, 1942, Jan.-June (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Reports and Studies, 1942, July-Dec. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Reports and Studies, 1943 and undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material
      - Published by the Children's Bureau
        - 1929-1940 (Box 16, Folder 7)
        - 1941, March (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - 1941, June - 1943 (Box 17, Folder 2)
        - undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
        - Received by the Children's Bureau
          - 1939-1940, Sept. (Box 80, Box 17, Folder 4)
          - 1940, Dec. (Box 17, Folder 5)
          - 1941 (Box 17, Folder 6)
          - 1941 (Box 17, Folder 7)
          - 1942, Jan.-Feb. (Box 18, Folder 1)
          - 1942, May (Box 18, Folder 2)
          - 1942, Sept. (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - 1943 (Box 18, Folder 4, Box 81)
      - Photographs. Unidentified rural families and houses, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Tulsa, Oklahoma
        - Memoranda and Notes on Out-of-School Minors, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Crystal City, Texas
        - Miscellany, 1938-1940 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Hidalgo County, Texas
        - Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 18, Folder 8)
        - Memoranda of Interviews with School Officials, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 9)
        - Memoranda of Interviews with Work Supervisors and Public Officials, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 10)
        - Writings. Draft of Hidalgo County Study, 1942 (Box 18, Folder 11)
        - Writings. Additional Drafts of Hidalgo County Study, 1942-1943 (Box 18, Folder 12)
        - Writings. Preliminary and Final Reports on Hidalgo County Study, 1941-1943 (Box 19, Folder 1)
        - Family Schedules. East Donna (Box 19, Folder 2)
        - Family Schedules. Edcouch - Elsa (Box 19, Folder 3)
        - Family Schedules. LaVilla (Box 19, Folder 4)
        - Family Schedules. Miscellany (Box 19, Folder 5)
        - Case Stories. General - Migration (Box 19, Folder 6)
        - Case Stories. Problems with Schools - Work of Children (Box 19, Folder 7)
        - Analysis of Educational Data (Box 19, Folder 8)
        - Analysis of Work Data (Box 19, Folder 9)
        - Selected Interpretive Material (Box 19, Folder 10)
        - Miscellany (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - Photographs, 1941.Negatives are filed in the Negative File. (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth Series, 1922-1966
      This is the largest series in the Warburton collection. It contains correspondence, reports, studies, clippings, printed material, photographs, and volumes from Warburton's sixteen-year tenure as executive secretary and director of research of the Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth. The organization disbanded in 1963.
      Approximately sixty percent of this series came to the library already organized. The remaining forty percent of the material was unorganized and had to be integrated into the organized material. With modifications and additions, the integration of the material was done using the original (1949) index to the office files as a guide.